(upbeat music)
- Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
My name is Marco.
- My name is Catherine and today we
are here with an advanced level lesson.
That means that we're
going to listen to it pretty long
and exciting dialogue and then we'll
talk a little bit about what you've heard
and some of these
cool, interesting phrases.
- That's right, today we have a
lesson about planning a crime.
We're planning a bank robbery.
- Ooh, my favorite.
There've been lots of movies about
this topic, very fun movies in, you know,
from the beginning of
movie making till now.
It's a very popular topic.
- That's right and I'm this
occasion as Catherine said.
It's a nice fun dialogue
and we're gonna have
a lot of colloquial terms
so maybe you won't
really understand a
couple of different phrases
because they're very colloquial,
they're very American terms.
And the accents are also
they're a little bit from like
Boston kind of like New
Jersey maybe or something.
- Right, so keep in ear out
for some of these strange
or unusual phrases, we
will be talking about them
in a moment but don't
worry if you don't understand
this dialogue the first time
you'll be hearing it again later.
(upbeat music)
All right, let's run through
this one more time from the top.
I will be positioned here across
from the bank on this park bench.
Now according to the
intel we got from Jimmy.
- Oh, who's Jimmy?
- Jeez, Ralph, pay attention, will ya?
Jimmy's our mole, you know?
The guy on the inside, he's been snooping
and passing on the info to us
so we can pull this high stuff.
- Yeah, Ralph, clean the
mothballs out of years and listen up.
This year's important, we don't
wanna end up back in the slam of Dua.
Your role is pretty important
here with dependent on you, man.
- Okay, okay, I'm listening, mothballs and...
- All righty then, where was I?
Oh yeah, okay, so I'll be on the lookout.
Sitting here on the bench
across from the bank,
nobody moves until I
give the go ahead, all right?
And what's the go ahead, Ralph?
- You, um, you, uh, oh yeah, you'll
take off your hat and scratch your head.
- Right, when I take my hat off
and scratch my head, you do what?
- Again, the box.
- Right, you get in the box,
I'll make sure it's all sealed
and then posing as the delivery guy, I'll
drop off a special package for the manager.
Now, according to Jimmy, the bank manages
leaving early on Tuesday 'cause
it's his wedding anniversary.
He and the wife are having
a romantic rendezvous
in the country, so any
packages delivered will be left
unopened in his office until it
gets back late on Wednesday.
- Which gives us access to
his office for at least 12 hours.
Okay, Ralph, this is where you come in.
Where are you?
- I'm standing right next to you, Sammy.
- Oh, sorry, Sammy, I'm in
the box, right here in that box.
- And what do you do once I
deliver you to the manager's office?
- I stay in the box until the bank is
closed and then I get out of the box.
- And then, what next, Ralph?
Oh, for Pete's sake, this
is never going to work.
- Hey, can be a chance here, fellas.
I correct the safe and
then, then I take the money
and then I, um, well,
I get back in the box.
At a boy, Ralph, in the
morning, I come back to the bank,
say there's been a mix
up with the delivery I
made and take the
special package back here.
- All right, let's get some sleep.
It's a big day tomorrow, fellas.
- A perfect plan, Sammy,
it went off without a hitch.
- Let's open this up and get Ralph out of
here so we can start counting the money.
- Feel, I'm sure I'm glad to see you guys.
I was sure getting
lonely with no one to talk.
That's nice, okay, how much?
- Oh, really?
Really, really, really glad.
- Money, Ralph, money.
- Oh, man, I knew I forgot something.
- Ah, damn it.
- All right, we're back, so
obviously this guy, Ralph,
I don't know why, always the one robber
whose name is Ralph is not very clever.
- No, it doesn't mean
that Ralphs are generally
not smart people, but
yeah, I think you're right.
There's usually, like
in bank robberies or
something, like for
example in the old movies,
always Ralph was the one
that was messing things up.
- Oh, Ralph.
Well, let's find out what
Ralph screwed up today.
First of all, we've got
the guys, Sammy, Ralph,
and Frankie who are
talking about the plan, okay?
And Sammy mentions that
he had the intel from Jimmy.
- Okay, so when we talk about intel,
we're talking about information, right?
- That's right, so
intel is a word that's
short for intelligence
or facts or information.
- That's right, so you
can talk about intelligence
as maybe you're very
smart, you're very intelligent,
but when we talk about intelligence,
we talk about gathering information
in order to help us
accomplish an objective.
- For example, in movies about the CIA,
we often hear them
talk about gathering intel.
That means collecting facts.
- Right, very good,
so they had intel from
Jimmy about the bank
and the layout, and well,
they were like, who's
Jimmy and Sammy says that?
Well, he's our mole, you
know, the guy on the inside.
- A mole, so mole is an animal,
but in cases of intelligence
or maybe in this case
a bank robbery, spying,
a mole is a person who's
basically stealing information.
So for example, if I work in the CIA,
but I'm selling information from the CIA
to the French government,
I'm a mole, right?
So you're basically like a spy.
- Yes.
- You're a person on
the inside and that's what
they mean when he says
he's our guy on the inside.
You're inside the enemy's territory
or you're inside their organization.
- Exactly, so for example,
have you seen the show 24?
- Yeah, with Jack Bauer.
- Well, they often have
this problem of moles
inside the organization,
so maybe the terrorists,
the terrorists have
a guy on the inside.
- That's right. - He's a mole.
- So they have somebody that has penetrated the organization.
- Exactly.
- Okay, so they talk about the mole and
how they are going to pull this heist off.
- Okay, so the phrase
here is to pull off a heist.
First of all, what's a heist?
- Well, a heist is a robbery
is a basically a robbery.
- Yeah, it's another word for robbery, so--
- It's kind of old though.
You don't really say it anymore, right?
- No, you can say it's a heist
movie or it's a movie about a heist.
It's almost like a genre, you know?
There's a basic storyline
where they plan the robbery
if they do the robbery,
something goes wrong.
What's going to happen, so that's a heist.
- Very good, so a heist is
something that was planned out.
Like a robbery that's planned out.
It's not really if you come up to someone
and say, give me your
wallet, that's not really a heist.
- No, that's a stick up,
but a heist is something
that you pull off, so
to pull off is to succeed.
- To accomplish. - To accomplish.
So I pulled it off, I was able to do it.
- So you pulled off the heist.
- Very good, and well,
they were talking about
if they do it, they don't
want to get caught
because they don't want
to go back to the slammer.
- The slammer.
- Yeah, well, I don't blame them.
I wouldn't want to go
to the slammer either.
- So what is the slammer?
- The slammer, the big house.
- Right, lock up the
slammer, the big house.
All these are colloquial
synonyms for prison, for jail.
- Jail, so normally we say prison or jail.
Like it's a maximum security prison.
Like prison break, the TV show.
But in colloquial English,
we often say slammer.
- Okay, the slammer or the big house.
- Okay, so they were
talking that they don't want
to go back to the slammer,
and now when they were
actually planning
out the crime, he says,
well, you wait until I
give you the go ahead.
- Okay, so this is the plan.
He's going to wait for a sign.
The go ahead means a sign that
indicates that it's time to do something.
Okay, so for example, so in
this case, what is that sign?
The sign or the go ahead is he'll
take off his hat and scratch his head.
- Okay, so that's a sign that
means it's okay to proceed,
it's okay to continue.
- Right.
- So you can also say,
okay, when we're ready
to go, Marco, I'll
give you the go ahead.
Okay, just wait for me to wait.
- Okay, very good.
So that's the go ahead, the signal.
- Exactly.
- All right, very good.
Now moving on, we have a
French word here, but it's used very
commonly in English, and they
said, okay, we have a rendezvous.
- Okay, so a rendezvous is a meetup
or a time or place where
people are connecting together.
So for example, in a heist, you
could say, we're going to rob the bank,
and then we will rendezvous at
our favorite restaurant in two hours.
- Okay, so rendezvous is me
to meet up to get together.
- Right, but in this case, they're
talking about a romantic rendezvous.
So this means a trip with a lover.
So it's a little bit different, right?
He and his wife are having a
romantic rendezvous in the country.
- Okay, that means that they're
going to have a romantic meeting.
- Uh-huh, okay, very good.
And now this next phrase
is very, very interesting.
It's very common to hear it as well.
I think like mom say it a lot.
Oh, for Pete's sake.
- Oh, for Pete's sake.
Well, I don't know who Pete is, honestly.
But this means my gosh, or
come on, or I'm so tired of this.
- So you're a little bit exasperated,
maybe you're a little bit irritated.
- Oh, for Pete's sake, Marcos.
Stop giving me examples.
I'm just, I'm done hearing them.
- Yeah.
So there are a lot of other
ways to say this, right?
- Yeah, so you could
say, for goodness sake.
- For goodness sake.
Or, oh, for heaven's sake.
- For heaven's sake.
And finally, for God's sake.
- Right.
- But this one, you have
to be careful because some
people who are religious
might be offended if you use it.
- So if that's the case and
you would just rather go
with Pete's sake, heaven's
sake, or goodness sake.
- Okay, for goodness sake.
- It's a very common phrase.
And as you say, it's for when
you're a little bit irritated.
It's like, oh, for goodness sake.
Stop complaining.
- Exactly.
- Okay.
And now for our last word, you
may have seen the word fellas, fellas.
- Fellas.
So this comes from the
word fellow person, man.
But oftentimes in these kind of
movies or stories about heists or crimes,
the men talk to each
other using the word fellas.
Or fellas.
So come on, fellas, let's go.
- That means come on,
guys, come on, everyone.
- Okay, yeah, so this is always about men,
not like a group of women would use this.
And it's something
that's a little bit older.
We don't really say this like, oh, me
and my fellas, we're gonna go to the store.
- You would say this
more in old time English.
- Yeah, you can see it maybe in some movies
when somebody comes
up and greets other
people, other guys, he
would say, hey, fellas.
- Exactly.
Or there's a mafia movie.
It's about the American
mafia called Good Fellas.
- Mm-hmm, very good.
- That's a very famous one.
So it kind of gives
you that feeling of an
older English like the
1940s for the 1970s.
- Okay, very good.
A lot of interesting things
going on in this bank robbery.
Why don't we go back,
listen to the dialogue one
last time, and we'll
be back in a little bit.
(upbeat music)
All right, let's run through
this one more time from the top.
I will be positioned here, across
from the bank on this park bench.
Now, according to the
intel, we got from Jimmy.
- Oh, who's Jimmy?
- Geez, Ralph, pay attention, will ya?
Jimmy's our mole, you know?
The guy on the inside, he's been snooping
and passing on the info to us
so we can pull this high stuff.
- Yeah, Ralph, clean the
mothballs out of years and listen up.
This year's important.
We don't wanna end up
back in the slam at Doo-ya.
Your role is pretty important
here, we're dependent on you, man.
- Okay, okay, I'm listening.
- More awesome.
- All righty then, where was I?
Oh yeah, okay.
So I'll be on the lookout, sitting here
on the bench across from the bank.
Nobody moves until I
give the go ahead, all right?
And what's the go ahead, Ralph?
- You, um, you, uh, oh yeah.
You'll take off your hat
and scratch your head.
- Right, when I take my hat off
and scratch my head, you do what?
- Again, the box.
- Right, you get in the box.
I'll make sure it's all sealed and
then posing as the delivery guy.
I'll drop off a special
package for the manager.
Now, according to Jimmy,
the bank managers leave in
early on Tuesday 'cause
it's his wedding anniversary.
He and the wife are having
a romantic rendezvous
in the country, so any
packages deliver will be left
unopened in his office until it
gets back late on Wednesday.
- Which gives us access to
his office for at least 12 hours.
Okay, Ralph, this is where you come in.
Where are you?
- I'm standing right next to you, Sammy.
Oh, sorry Sam, I'm in the
box right here in that box.
And what do you do once I
deliver you to the manager's office?
- I stay in the box until the bank is
closed, and then I get out of the box.
- And then, what next, Ralph?
Oh, for Pete's sake, this
is never going to work.
- Hey, give me a chance here, fellows.
I correct the safe, and
then then I take the money,
and then I get back in the box.
- At a boy, Ralph, in the morning, I come
back to the bank, say there's been a mix up
with the delivery I made, and
take the special package back here.
- All right, let's get some sleep.
It's a big day tomorrow, fellas.
- A perfect plan, Sammy,
it went off without a hitch.
- Let's open this up, and get Ralph out of
here so we can start counting the money.
- Feel, I'm sure I'm glad to see you guys.
I was sure getting
lonely with no one to talk.
- That's nice, okay, how much?
- Really, really, really, really glad.
- Money, Ralph, money.
- Oh, man, I knew I forgot something.
- Ah, damn it.
- Okay, so, someone
proclaimed at the end of the
dialogue that everything
went off without a hitch.
- Mm-hmm, is this true?
- No, what does it mean if
something went without a hitch?
- It went off without a hitch means
there was not even one problem.
It went off, it went perfectly.
- Smoothly.
- Smoothly, yes.
- Okay.
- And it didn't, because, well,
these robbers didn't actually rob any.
- Right, he forgot to get the money.
- Right, so it's kind of an idiot.
- Right, but there are
actually a lot of good movies.
I think the most
recent one about main
robberies is Ocean's 11,
Ocean's 12, Ocean's 13.
- Yeah, that's right, those
are all about big heists.
- Big heists, and I think they mentioned
the word "hist" a couple
of times in that movie.
- Yeah, definitely.
So there was a movie
with Clive Owen a few
years ago called "The
Inside Man" that was maybe
one of the best heist movies
I've seen in a long time.
- Yeah, that was a really good movie.
I think also Swordfish was a pretty
good movie with Johnson Walter.
- Yeah, I remember that one too.
- Yeah, I like it when
the bad guys win, you
know, 'cause it's a little
bit more interesting.
- Yeah, I guess you could say that.
- I don't think the public likes this.
- Well, in "The Inside Man,"
the bad guy is kind of
a good guy, but he wins.
- Uh-huh. - Yeah, I like that.
- Yeah, so, but it's a
very interesting topic,
and I don't know, I haven't really heard of
many bank robberies nowadays anymore.
- Not so much, I think
security in banks is pretty good,
but I'd be very curious
to hear from our users
if they have any favorite heist stories
or movies, real or fake, both are okay.
You can let us know on
our website, Englishpa.com.
- That's right, all right,
we'll see everyone there.
- Bye. - Bye.
(upbeat music)